Every kid knows the phrase, [kid sing-songy] "Trick or treat!" But have you
ever stopped to wonder — what kind of _"or"_ is that, exactly?
Let's start with the obvious interpretation: Two circles—two children. Orange means
treats, gray means tricks. This is inclusive OR: If any child
knocks, everyone gets candy. Only an empty porch gets tricks.
[quickly] [chuckles] Is this how Venn diagrams work? Not at all!
But hey, it's Halloween—logic gets to wear a costume, too.
[title] Trick AND Treat Both children must show up together, or
nobody gets treats. [sarcastic] One lonely kid? Sorry, that's a trick.
[title] Trick XOR Treat This house rewards exactly one visitor.
Too few or too many, and everyone gets tricked.
These three behaviors cover most houses on the block.
But De Morgan's laws hint at something more... a
theoretical complement to each. A spooky, inverted reflection.
[spooky] What cursed operations lurk in the penumbra of reason?
Let's face our fears and venture into the dark.
[title] Trick NOR Treat: the Halloween hater. This neighbor
only gives treats when nobody visits. [quick laugh] The
only winning move is not to play.
[title] Trick NAND Treat: NOT-AND—the reverse psychology neighbor. This
house gives treats to everyone... except pairs. Come alone?
Treats. Don't come at all? ...[chuckles] Also Treats. Come
together? [mischievous] That's the only way to get tricked.
[title] Trick XNOR Treat: the conformity enforcer—XOR inverted. This neighbor
rewards matching behavior. Both kids visit, or both stay home?
Treats. Just one kid? [judgmental] That's a trick.
These bottom-row operations are... deeply strange. They're the
kinds of houses you'd skip entirely. But mathematically?
They're just as valid as the classics.
So the next time a child asks [kid sing-songy]
"trick or treat?", you now have the mathematically correct
response: [annoying high-pitched nasal pedantic] "That depends—which logical operator
are you implementing?" [quick laugh] ...though I wouldn't recommend
it if you don't want your house getting egged.